Finding Aid for Department of Economics (University of Michigan) records, 1915-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Economics (University of Michigan) records
1915-1980
University of Michigan. Department of Economics.
87141 Bimu C26 2
Records, 1915-1980,of the department of economics of the University of Michigan; contain files of chairmen, Isaiah Sharfman, Gardner Ackley, and Warren Smith, including minutes of staff meetings, research materials, and administrative records; also papers collected and interviews conducted by Marjorie Brazer with present and past faculty of the department in connection with its centennial.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from donors nos. 5205 and 4717.
The record group is open without restriction.
The teaching of political economy was provided for in Judge Woodward's "Catholepistemiad" scheme drawn up in 1817, which formed the basis for the University of Michigan. Until the appointment of Henry Carter Adams as lecturer in political economy in 1880, the current professor of moral and intellectual philosophy, who was nearly always the senior member of the faculty or the president, had taught the course. Adams became a full professor in 1887, and headed what became the Department of Economics until his death in 1921. Classes in business and industry were separated from the Department of Economics and eventually became the nucleus for the School of Business Administration, which was founded in 1924. Courses in sociology were similarly split off into the Department of Sociology in 1931. A centennial history, compiled in 1979, is available in the collection.
The bulk of the Department of Economics records, covering the period 1950-1980, contain files of the chairmen, Isaiah Sharfman, Gardner Ackley, and Warren Smith. Included are executive committee and staff meeting minutes, budgets, faculty appointments, schedules, salaries, and reports on building needs. Additional materials cover the work of various centers and professional organizations.
Subjects:
Economics.; University of Michigan. Department of Economics.
Contributors:
Oral histories.; Ackley, Gardner.; Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-1984; Bluestone, Barry.; Brazer, Harvey E., 1922-1991; Dernberger, Robert F.; Fowler, Ann Schwartz Smith.; Freedman, Deborah S.; Fusfeld, Daniel R. (Daniel Roland), 1922-2007; Haber, Fannie.; Haber, William, 1899-1988.; Hymans, Saul H.; Katona, George, 1901-1981; Klein, Lawrence Robert.; Levinson, Harold Myer, 1919-; Morgan, James.; Mueller, Eva, 1920-; Palmer, William B.; Peterson, Shorey, 1897-1981.; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-; Steiner, Peter Otto, 1922-; Stolper, Wolfgang F.; Suits, Daniel Burbidge, 1918-; Sharfman, I. Leo (Isaiah Leo), 1886-1969; Smith, Warren Lounsbury, 1914-1972.; Brazer, Marjorie Cahn.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.
- Records
  - Universities -- National Bureau Committee for Economic Research, 1940-1959; 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation, 1955-1960; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation (cont.), 1955-1960; 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Departmental Organization, 1934-1951 (Box 2)
  - Time Schedules, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Regional Faculty Research Seminar, 1960; 29 folders (Box 2)
  - Conference on the Economic Outlook, 1953-1961; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Meetings of Department Chairmen, 1954-1961; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Research Committee, Social Sciences, 1948-1951; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - American Economic Association, 1952-1960; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Center for Research on Economic Development, 1956-1962; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Department Reports, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1958-1959; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics, 1952-1960 (Box 3)
  - Student Placement, 1954-1960; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Doctoral Committee and Exams, 1950-1952; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Building needs, 1928-1948 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Graduate Programs, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Research and Health Problems of the Aged, 1959-1961 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Social Science Personnel, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Conference on Medical Economics, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Conference on Research on Economic Stability, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous), 1961-1962 (Box 4)
  - Current Economic Research, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Departmental Luncheons, 1953-1955 (Box 4)
  - Departmental Election Statistics, 1915-1921 (Box 4)
  - Fellowships, 1954; 1962-1963; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation Contract -- RSQE, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation Grant -- Area Studies Program, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Graduate Degree Requirements, 1954-1956 (Box 4)
  - Graduate Work in Economics at other institutions, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Great Lakes Regional Assemblies, 1960 (Box 4)
  - International Cooperation Administration -- Korean Project, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Interviews, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Italian Centennial Program, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Readings in Economics, 1955-1960 (Box 4)
  - Research (misc.), 1955 (Box 4)
  - Research Advisory Committee, 1959-1961 (Box 4)
  - Research and Publications, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Report on Courses and Staffing, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Social Science Study Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Summer Session, 1950; 1962; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Theory Examination -- Business Administration and Economics, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Urban Community Program and Seminar, 1941-1947 (Box 4)
- Departmental Centennial
  - Manuscript of history of economics department by Marjorie Brazer (Box 5)
    (includes appendices and other background material)
  - Responses to centennial invitations (Box 5)
    (includes remembrances of economic department)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Tapes and transcripts of interviews compiled in preparation of centennial history, 1979
    - Ackley, Gardner (Box 5)
    - Angell, Robert Cooley (Box 5)
    - Bluestone, Barry (Box 5)
    - Brazer, Harvey (Box 5)
    - Dernberger, Robert (Box 5)
    - Fowler, Ann Schwartz Smith (Box 5)
    - Freedman, Deborah S (Box 5)
    - Fusfeld, Daniel (Box 5)
    - Haber, Fannie (Box 5)
    - Haber, William (Box 5)
    - Hymans, Saul (Box 5)
    - Katona, George (Box 5)
    - Klein, Lawrence (Box 5)
    - Levinson, Harold (Box 5)
    - Morgan, James (Box 5)
    - Mueller, Eva (Box 5)
    - Palmer, William B (Box 5)
    - Peterson, Shorey (Box 5)
    - Shapiro, Harold (Box 5)
      (not to be quoted)
    - Steiner, Peter (Box 5)
    - Stolper, Wolfgang (Box 5)
    - Suits, Daniel (Box 5)
- Minutes and Memoranda
  - Executive Committee, 1953-1974; 19 folders (Box 6)
  - Departmental (Staff) Meetings
    - 1954-1962, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - 1967-March 1973, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - April 1973-April 1974, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Undated (Box 7)
- Chairmen's Files
  - Correspondence, 1964-1974; 11 folders (Box 7)
  - Budgets, 1956-1973; 12 folders (Box 7)
- Topical Files
  - Committees
    - Assignments and miscellanea, 1967-1972 (Box 8)
    - Career Advancement Committee, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1968-1970 (Box 8)
    - Graduate Program Committee, 1968-1973 (Box 8)
  - Faculty
    - General
      - Appointments and Schedules, 1968-1970 (Box 8)
      - Effort Reports, 1966-1973 (Box 8)
    - Merit Increases, 1968-1970; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Salaries
      - 1964 (Box 8)
      - 1967-1969, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Report on Salary Determination Procedures, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Building, 1968-1972 (Box 8)
    - Center for Research on Economic Development, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Courses, 1968-1970 (Box 8)
    - Joint Degree, Law and Economics, Grant Request, 1970-1974 (Box 8)
    - New Degrees, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Outlook Conference, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
    - Political Economy, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Political Science and Economics Degree, 1970-1972 (Box 8)
    - Population Studies Center, 1967-1971 (Box 8)
    - Program Evaluation Report, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
    - Public Policy Studies, 1968-1973 (Box 8)
    - Terminal Master's Program, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
    - Undergraduate Program, 1971-1973 (Box 8)